I hope you all are doing very well.
आशा करता हूं आप सब बहुत अच्छे होंगे।
My name is Siddhant Agnihotri.
मेरा नाम है सिद्धांत अग्निहोत्री स्टडी
Welcome to Study Close.  So
क्लोज पर आपका बहुत-बहुत स्वागत है। तो
friends, in what way has Pakistan
दोस्तों किस तरीके से पाकिस्तान ने ईरान
betrayed Iran?  Let's talk.
को धोखा दिया है। चलिए हम बात करते हैं।
But the combo of Personality Development plus Chanakya
लेकिन पर्सनालिटी डेवलपमेंट प्लस चाणक्य
Niti, this lecture, i.e. this
नीति का कॉम्बो ये लेक्चर मतलब यह जो
course, the link of the description is given in the comment box.
कोर्स है डिस्क्रिप्शन कमेंट बॉक्स में
You can cancel this course.
लिंक दिया है। आप इस कोर्स को अेल कर सकते
We have launched an offer for one day.
हैं। एक दिन के लिए हमने ऑफर निकाला है।
This course costs only ₹500.  Use coupon code SUMMER.
मात्र ₹500 का ये कोर्स है। समर कूपन कोड
So look friend,
यूज़ करें। तो देखो यार जो पाकिस्तान ने
Iran will take 110% revenge for whatever Pakistan did.  Is it
किया ईरान उसका 110% बदला लेगा। क्या यह
a balancing act?  Now Pakistan is
एक बैलेंसिंग एक्ट है? अब पाकिस्तान भारत
becoming India, okay it's okay.  We will take help from America as well
बन रहा है कि चलो ठीक है। हम अमेरिका से
as from China and the
भी मदद लेंगे, चाइना से भी मदद लेंगे और
work will be done.  But friends, it is
काम जो है वो हो जाएगा। लेकिन दोस्तों ये
not working like this because the real
ऐसे चल नहीं रहा है क्योंकि इस समय असली
war is going on at this time.  This is not a proxy war
युद्ध चालू है। यह कोई प्रॉक्सी वॉर नहीं
that Pakistan can escape by taking a narrow path.
है जो पाकिस्तान पतली गली लेके निकल ले।
Now they have given strong rhetorical support
अब इन्होंने स्ट्रांग रेटोरिक सपोर्ट तो
to Iran that no, no, we are
दिया है ईरान को कि नहीं नहीं हम तो आपके
with you.  Shabaz Sharif had said that you should
साथ हैं। शबाज शरीफ तो बोल के आए थे कि आप
say that we did not carry out the Palgaon attack
ये बोलिए कि जो पैलगांव हमला है हमने नहीं
and we will also give you nuclear missiles.
कराया और हम आपको न्यूक्लियर मिसाइल भी दे
And when one of his IRGC
देंगे। और जब इन्हीं के आईआरजीसी के एक
members spoke about this, he backed off and changed the party.
मेंबर ने बोला तो पीछे हट गए पार्टी बदल
So whatever rules this civilized
लिए। तो जितने भी रूल्स ये सिविलाइज्ड
behavior and international humanitarian law
बिहेवियर एंड इंटरनेशनल ह्यूमैनिटेरियन लॉ
says, he is valeting them all.  So, in a
कहता है वो सब वलेट कर रहा है। मतलब एक
way, Israel is making a big mess.   He is
तरीके से इजराइल बहुत गड़बड़ कर रहा है।
doing something very wrong.  But during the same time, Asim
बहुत गलत कर रहा है। लेकिन उसी दौरान आसिम
Munir has lunch with Donald Trump.
मुनीर जो हैं वो डोनल्ड ट्रंप के साथ लंच
Scratch the chicken.  So basically what
खाते हैं। चिकन नोचते हैं। तो बेसिकली ये
you are seeing, this double standard, this
जो आप देख रहे हो ना ये डबल स्टैंडर्ड ये
duplicity is what Pakistan has been
दोगलापन है पाकिस्तान का जो कि ये हमेशा
doing since always.  Now Iran will remember this betrayal.
से करता आया है। अब ईरान को धोखा ये ईरान
Ok?  Ishqdar, their Foreign
याद रखेगा। ठीक है? इशकदार इनके जो फॉरेन
Minister immediately said that no
मिनिस्टर हैं उन्होंने तुरंत बोल दिया कि
such statement has
ऐसा कोई भी स्टेटमेंट जो है वो हमारी तरफ
come from our side.  Immediately means without even thinking for a second.
से नहीं आया है। तुरंत मतलब एक सेकंड भी
So brother, now Asim Munir has
तो भाई अब जैसे आसिम मुनीर है वो इस समय
gone and sat right in the lap of America
अमेरिका की बिल्कुल गोद में जाकर बैठ गए
and Iran can see this clearly.  By the way, let
और ईरान को ये साफ-साफ दिख रहा है। वैसे
me tell you that Iran has opened its airspace for India for
मैं बता दूं कि भारत के लिए ईरान ने अपना
some time because thousands of
एयर स्पेस खोल दिया कुछ देर के लिए हजार
more students are to be evacuated.
जो स्टूडेंट्स को और इवाकुएट किया जाना
So this balancing act is going to be so
है। तो ये जो बैलेंसिंग एक्ट है ये कितना
dangerous.  Let's talk.
खतरनाक होने वाला है। चलिए बात करते हैं।
First of all, you know that the
सबसे पहले तो आपको पता है कि जो पाकिस्तान
relationship between Pakistan and Iran is quite
और ईरान के रिलेशनशिप है ना वो काफी
complex.  You can see it, this
कॉम्प्लेक्स है। ये आपको दिख रहा है ना ये
shaded area is called entire
जो शेडेड एरिया है इसको कहते हैं पूरा
Balochistan and the Baloch say
बलूचिस्तान और जो बलोच है ना वो कहते हैं
that the entire area is ours.  Now this is
कि पूरा एरिया हमारा है। अब ये पाकिस्तान
Balochistan of Pakistan where Balochistan Liberation
का बलूचिस्तान जहां पे बलूचिस्तान लिबरेशन
Army is there, this is Jaish al Adl, this is Shistan
आर्मी ये है जैश अल अदल ये शिस्तान
Balochistan.  This is an area of ​​Iran.  You may
बलूचिस्तान है। ईरान का एरिया है। आपको
remember that
याद होगा कि
last year both countries
पिछले साल दोनों देशों ने एक दूसरे के ऊपर
fired missiles at each other.  Both Iran and Pakistan
मिसाइल मारी थी। दोनों ईरान और पाकिस्तान
clashed with each other.  And since then the relationship had become
भिड़ गए थे आपस में। और तभी से रिलेशनशिप
very bad.  Now that is a lie
बहुत खराब हो गए थे। अब वो तो खैर झूठ की
that no, the relationships are good.
बात है कि नहीं नहीं अच्छे हैं रिलेशनशिप।
But the terrorists here
लेकिन यहां के जो आतंकवादी वो यहां पे
attack here and the terrorists here, that is the
हमला करते हैं और यहां के आतंकवादी मतलब
militants, attack here.
जो मिलिटेंट्स हैं वो यहां पे हमला करते
So both of them keep blaming each other
हैं। तो दोनों एक दूसरे को आरोप लगाते
that what you have is
रहते हैं कि तुम्हारा जो है वो हमारे
making ours unstable and what yours has is making ours
अनस्टेबल कर रहा है और तुम्हारा हमारे
unstable.  But the truth is
अनस्टेबल कर रहा है। लेकिन सच्चाई तो ये
friends that they want a whole United
है दोस्तों कि ये पूरा एक यूनाइटेड
Balochistan and if Iran goes then
बलूचिस्तान चाहते हैं और अगर ईरान गया तो
you can assume that this area will be
आप ये मान के चलिए कि इस एरिया पे तो
occupied by Jaish-e-Mohammed and after that
कब्जा हो जाएगा जैशदल का और उसके बाद
Pakistan's Balochistan will be in danger.
पाकिस्तान का बलचिस्तान खतरे में आ जाएगा।
So the relationship which is between the two Islamic countries and the
तो रिलेशनशिप जो दोनों इस्लामिक कंट्रीज
Islamic Republic,
के बीच में है ना इस्लामिक रिपब्लिक के
I will tell you
बीच में आपको मैं बताता हूं कि ईरान ने
what Iran has done for Pakistan and okay
क्या किया है पाकिस्तान के लिए और ठीक है
friends you will reap what you sow
दोस्तों आप जो जैसा करोगे वैसा भरोगे
but we also supported Iran in 1979
लेकिन 1979 का ईरान का हम इसलिए भी सपोर्ट
because
देते हैं पाकिस्तान को क्योंकि पाकिस्तान
see Pakistan had begged from everyone, so Pakistan
देखिए भीख मांगी है उसने सबसे सो
knew that we would not be able to do anything on our own, so
पाकिस्तान को पता था कि हम अपने से तो कुछ
we immediately
कर नहीं पाएंगे तो तुरंत हम उसने अमेरिका
chose America and said that we will go with America.
को चुन लिया कि हम अमेरिका के साथ जाएंगे।
India remained non-aligned but Pakistan
भारत नॉन एलाइंड रहा है लेकिन पाकिस्तान
immediately chose the US.  Now
ने तुरंत ही अमेरिका को चुन लिया। अब
because Iran was also a stooge of America at that time.
क्योंकि ईरान भी उस समय अमेरिका का पिट्ठू
Iran did whatever America said.
था। जो अमेरिका कहता था वो ईरान करता था।
Reza Shah Pahlavi was the one who was
रेजा शाह पहलवी जो थे वो अमेरिका ने ही
put in power by America.  So it is obvious that
उनको बैठाया था। तो जाहिर सी बात है कि
Pakistan will definitely support Iran
इसलिए पाकिस्तान ईरान को सपोर्ट करेगा ही
and Iran will do everything that makes
करेगा और ईरान हर वो चीज करेगा जिससे
both Pakistan and America happy.   The
पाकिस्तान और अमेरिका दोनों खुश हो।
location of Pakistan is very strategic.
पाकिस्तान की लोकेशन बड़ी स्ट्रेटेजिक है।
That's why every country needs that country.  So what
इसलिए हर देश को वो देश चाहिए। तो अब क्या
happened now is that Iran became the first country to
हुआ कि यहां पे पहला देश बना ईरान जिसने
immediately recognise Pakistan
पाकिस्तान को तुरंत रिकॉग्नाइज़्ज़ किया
in 1947.  Nothing happens by creating a country.   On
1947 में। देश बनाने से कुछ नहीं होता।
the other hand, Nityananda is also roaming around the country.
उधर नित्यानंद भी देश बना के घूम रहे हैं।
You can also make your own country but unless you get recognition, it makes
जब तक रिकॉग्निशन ना मिले आप भी अपना देश
no sense.
बना सकते हैं तब तक कोई मतलब नहीं है।
Taiwan is so developed but it has
ताइवान इतना डेवलप्ड है लेकिन अभी तक उसको
not yet received recognition.  Are you understanding?  The
रिकॉग्निशन नहीं मिला है। समझ रहे हो? जिस
day I got recognition.  Countries have started
दिन रिकॉग्निशन मिल गया। देशों ने
recognizing and now recognition means
रिकॉग्नाइज़ करना कर अब रिकॉग्नाइज़ मतलब
membership of the United Nations.  Then the
यूनाइटेड नेशन की मेंबरशिप हो गई। फिर
embassy had to be opened and many other relations were also
एम्बेसी खोलना हो गया और बहुत सारी और भी
established.  So unless that
चीजें रिलेशंस हो गया। तो जब तक वो नहीं
happens, no country gets recognised.
होता तब तक कोई देश रिकॉग्नाइज़ नहीं होता।
So Iran immediately said that yes, we
तो ईरान ने तुरंत बोला कि हां हम तुमको
recognize you in 1947 and
रिकॉग्नाइज़ करते हैं 1947 में और
Pakistan still has
पाकिस्तान ने इजराइल को अभी तक उसके
very bad relations with Israel.  Has not been recognised.
रिलेशनशिप बहुत खराब है। रिकॉग्नाइज़ नहीं
In those 1965 and 1971 wars, Iran
किया है। उन 1965 और 1971 वॉर में ईरान ने
gave full support to Pakistan and
पाकिस्तान को भरभर के सपोर्ट दिया और
why not, brother?
क्यों ना दे भैया? अमेरिका ने जो बोला था
America completely supported whatever it said.
अमेरिका तो बिल्कुल ही सपोर्ट में आ गया
America was preparing to launch a nuclear attack on India.
था ना। अमेरिका तो भारत पे न्यूक्लियर
Brother, we had signed a friendship treaty with the USSR enterprise and
भैया हमने फ्रेंडशिप ट्रीटी साइन कर करके
they
रखी हुई थी सोवियत से कि उन्होंने अपना
sent their war fleet.  900 Km  This
जंगी बेड़ा भेज दिया। 900 कि.मी. का
is the border, friends.  Which is of Iran and Pakistan's
बॉर्डर है दोस्तों। ईरान और पाकिस्तान का
Balochistan.  Do you understand?  And
जो बलूचिस्तान का है। आप समझ रहे हो? और
so far there have been 15 border clashes in the last 10
अभी तक 15 बॉर्डर क्लशेस हुई है पिछले 10
years.  And then Iran and
सालों में। और उसके बाद जो ईरान और
Pakistan, historically they have been
पाकिस्तान है हिस्टोरिकली अफगानिस्तान को
deferred regarding Afghanistan.  Now Iran
लेकर दे हैव बीन डिफर्ड। अब जैसे ईरान एक
is a Shia majority country.  Now when the Taliban
शिया मेजॉरिटी मुल्क है। अब जब तालीबान
came and when the Taliban was fighting, when there was civil
आया और तालीबान जब लड़ भी रहा था जब सिविल
war in Afghanistan from 1991 to 1996, the
वॉर थी 1991 से लेकर 1996 तक अफगानिस्तान
Taliban would always be
में तो तालीबान जो है वो तो शिया के
against the Shias.  We also get to see the persecution of Shia.
अगेंस्ट रहेगा। शिया का पर्सक्यूशन भी
Iran supports the
हमको देखने को मिलता है। ईरान ने सपोर्ट
Northern Alliance which
किया नॉर्दन अलायंस को जो कि तालीबान के
fights against the Taliban.  Anti-Taliban
खिलाफ लड़ा रहता है। एंटी तालिबान
forces.  From here the relations between both Pakistan and Iran
फोर्सेस। यहां से पाकिस्तान और ईरान के
started to crack.
दोनों के रिश्तों में दरार आनी शुरू हुई।
Because Pakistan was supporting the Taliban.
क्योंकि पाकिस्तान तालिबान को सपोर्ट कर
After that, the
रहा था। फिर उसके बाद पाकिस्तान की जो
relationship that Pakistan has with Saudi Arabia is that
रिलेशनशिप है सऊदी अरेबिया से वो एक तो
all the Sunni madrasas and the network are
जितने भी सुन्नी मदरसे हैं जो नेटवर्क है
funded by Saudi Arabia, somewhere or the other.
ना वो कहीं ना कहीं सऊदी अरेबिया उसको फंड
Does Saudi Arabia
करता है। कहीं ना कहीं क्या सऊदी अरेबिया
fund him somewhere?  So the Sunni sectarian
उसको फंड करता है। तो सुन्नी सेक्टेरियन
groups in Pakistan
ग्रुप्स जो पाकिस्तान में है वो इसी
study in these madrasas and persecute the Shia minority.  Are
मदरसों में पढ़ते हैं और शिया माइनॉरिटी
you understanding?  So it has been a very complex relationship.
हो? तो काफी कॉम्प्लेक्स रिलेशनशिप रही
But definitely Iran does
है। लेकिन डेफिनेटली ईरान कोई पाकिस्तान
not consider Pakistan a very good friend.  Ok.
को बहुत अच्छा दोस्त नहीं मानता। ठीक है।
Now you will say, Sir, his support is visible.  It is
अब आप बोलेंगे सर सपोर्ट तो उसका दिखता
definitely visible because Pakistan has
है। बिल्कुल दिखता है क्योंकि पाकिस्तान
promised everyone that our
ने सबसे यह वादा किया है कि हमारा जो
nuclear bomb is a Muslim bomb.  If there is
न्यूक्लियर बम है ना वो मुस्लिम बम है। तो
any problem we will come.  But friends,
कोई प्रॉब्लम हुई हम आएंगे। लेकिन दोस्तों
this doesn't belong to anyone.  These are only worth America's
ये किसी के नहीं है। ये सिर्फ अमेरिका के
money.  They will come for money.  Now if
पैसे के हैं। पैसे पे के आ जाएंगे ये। अब
we talk about the American angle, then the
अमेरिकन एंगल की हम बात करते हैं तो जो
condition of Iran after America in 1979.  Is it
ईरान अमेरिका 1979 के बाद जो हाल हुआ है
okay?  Which is their military and
ईरान का। ठीक है ना? जो इनका मिलिटरी और
financial dependency on Washington,
फाइनेंशियल डिपेंडेंसी है वाशिंगटन पे
especially of Pakistan.  So that is the current
पाकिस्तान के स्पेशली। तो वो इस समय करंट
situation because Pakistan knows that it
कौश क्योंकि पाकिस्तान को पता है कि वो
is on the verge of economic collapse and if
इकोनमिक कोलैप्स के कगार पे है और अगर
America does not support us then
अमेरिका ने हमको सपोर्ट नहीं किया तो
we are going to be finished.  Right?  After 91,
हमारी बैंड बजने वाली है। राइट? 91 के बाद
Pakistan had a very big base.
पाकिस्तान जो है बहुत बड़ा बेस रहा था।
All the airplanes and
अमेरिकन मिलिट्री जितने भी एरोप्लेनस है
fighter jets of the American military used to fly from Pakistan
ना फाइटर जेट्स वो पाकिस्तान से उड़ान
and they also raised the Mujahideen.
भरते थे और मुजाहदीन को भी इन्होंने खड़ा
Well, everybody knows that.
किया है। वो तो खैर सभी को ही पता है।
Under Operation Cyclone,
ऑपरेशन साइक्लोन के तहत बिलियंस एंड
they get billions and billions of dollars.
बिलियंस ऑफ डॉलर्स जो है वो इनको मिलते
So in a way America also has
हैं। तो एक तरीके से अमेरिका का भी इनके
reliance on them.  Let me tell you this as well.  America
ऊपर रिलायंस है। ये भी बता दूं। अमेरिका
also knows that if we have to control this region of
को भी पता है कि अगर हमको इस रीजन को
West Asia, then either
वेस्ट एशिया को कंट्रोल करना है तो या तो
we need the support of Afghanistan or we
हमको अफगानिस्तान का सहारा चाहिए या हमको
need the support of Pakistan.
पाकिस्तान का सहारा चाहिए। इन दोनों देश
We want one of these two countries.  India will
में से हमको कोई एक चाहिए। भारत जो है वो
never give away its airbase.  India itself is
कभी अपना एयरबेस देगा नहीं। भारत खुद ही
a very powerful country.  What to do?  So,
एक बहुत ताकतवर देश है। क्या करें? तो
in 2011-91, that is to say, the attacks of 2000 and September 11, 2001,
2011 91 में मतलब 2000 सितंबर 11 2001 के
America welcomed them.
जो अटैक्स हुए तो उसमें अमेरिका ने वेलकम
In 2021, Neto pulled out.  That
किया। 2021 में का नेटो ने पुल आउट कर
means all the NATO forces have
लिया। मतलब सारी नेटो फोर्सेस जो है वो
left.  Now Afghanistan's war on terror is
चली गई। अब अफगानिस्तान का वॉर ऑन टेरर
over.  Then the Pakistan band
खत्म हो गया। फिर पाकिस्तान की बैंड बजनी
started playing.  And if you see, during that time
शुरू हुई। और उसी दौरान अगर आप देखो तो
Pakistan had also done ceasefire with India.
पाकिस्तान ने भारत के साथ सीज फायर भी
China-centric Indo-Pacific
किया था। चाइना सेंट्रिक इंडोपेसिफिक
objectives became
ऑब्जेक्टिव जो थे वो पाकिस्तान के लिए
increasingly important for Pakistan.  In fact friends,
बहुत ज्यादा जरूरी हो गए। इनफैक्ट दोस्तों
when Joe Biden came, now you will call him useless,
जब जो बाइडन आए अब आप जो बाइडन को बेकार
but brother Donald Trump was
बोलेंगे लेकिन कम भाई डोनल्ड ट्रंप तो
very right, in his last
बहुत सही थे वो उन्होंने पिछ अपने जो
tenure of four years, he did
कार्यकाल रहा उनका चार सालों का एक भी
not meet even one Pakistani leader and kept
पाकिस्तान लीडर से मुलाकात नहीं की और
his relations at the lowest level.
अपने लोएस्ट लेवल पे इनके रिलेशन गए।
Pakistan also came to FATF.  Now Iran is
एफएटीएफ में भी पाकिस्तान आया। अब ईरान जो
in danger at this time and Pakistan has
है इस समय खतरे में है और पाकिस्तान ने जो
not fulfilled the promise it made.
वादा किया है उसको तो निभाया नहीं।
Nothing happens with retolic support.
रेटोलिक सपोर्ट से कुछ होता नहीं है।
Asim Munir is such a crazy man that after going to America, he is
अमेरिका में जाके आसिम मुनीर इतना पागल
saying that we will
आदमी है वहां पे जाके बोल रहा है कि हम तो
give whatever support to Iran.  He
ईरान को जो है वो सपोर्ट देंगे। इजराइल को
condemns Israel and is sitting there eating lunch.
कंडेम करता है और बैठ के वहां पे लंच खा
Friends, let me tell you that these
रहा है। दोस्तों आपको बता दूं कि जो ये
spy planes have been
स्पाई प्लेेंस हैं जो उसको पाकिस्तान ने
given shelter by Pakistan.  Pakistan has
पनाह दी हुई है। पाकिस्तान ने अमेरिकन
given its airspace to American planes and is
प्लेेंस को अपना एयर स्पेस दिया है और ये
saying that we will help Iran.  So
कह रहे हैं कि हम ईरान की मदद करेंगे। तो
forget it, it's never going to happen.  Are
यह भूल जाइए कभी नहीं होने वाला। समझ रहे
you understanding?  Trump is now telling the Pakistanis
हो? पाकिस्तानियों को अब ट्रंप कह रहे हैं
that Pakistanis
कि पाकिस्तानियों को ईरान के बारे में
know a lot about Iran.  I know everything about them.
बहुत कुछ पता है। सब कुछ पता है इनके बारे
Right?
में। राइट?
Well, what should India do?  Look, the
अच्छा भारत क्या करे? देखिए भारत का जो
view point of India is that the first thing that
व्यू पॉइंट है सबसे पहली बात तो ये है कि
India has said about isolating Pakistan should be done
भारत ने जो पाकिस्तान को आइसोलेट करने की
diplomatically.  The
बात कही है डिप्लोमेटिकली उसको करना
manner in which America has shown bragging after Operation Sindoor has been
चाहिए। ऑपरेशन सिंदूर के बाद जिस तरीके से
completely discredited by India saying that it is nonsense.
ने पूरा डिस्क्रेडिट दिया है कि यह बकवास
We did not say anything like that.  Is it okay
है। हमने ऐसा कुछ भी नहीं बोला। ठीक है
?  This Don Trump is like that and
ना? यह डॉन्ड ट्रंप जो है वो और सीधा-सीधा
Narendra Modi told him straight on his face.   In
नरेंद्र मोदी ने इसको मुंह पे बोल दिया।
fact, he even rejected the invitation.
इनफैक्ट इनविटेशन तक जो है वो ठुकरा दिया।
So Pakistan will always do this through American mediation
तो पाकिस्तान ने अमेरिकन मीडिएशन वो हमेशा
and
से यही करेगा और नोबेल पीस प्राइज के लिए
it has even nominated Donald Trump for the Nobel Peace Prize.
भी उसने डोनल्ड ट्रंप को नॉमिनेट कर दिया
Why did you nominate?  Because he knows
है। क्यों नॉमिनेट किया? क्योंकि उसको पता
that we won't be able to do it.  We
है कि हमसे ना हो पाएगा। हम अकेले दम पे
cannot kill India on our own.  It will become very difficult.
भारत को नहीं मार सकते। बहुत मुश्किल हो
We need four to five countries that can at
जाएगी। हमको चार पांच देश चाहिए जो कम से
least counter India, and anyway,
कम भारत को काउंटर करें और वैसे भी
forget about the military side, do it diplomatically.  Ok
मिलिट्री तो भूल जाइए डिप्लोमेटिकली। ठीक
?  Iran has been a very important element in
है? ईरान एक बहुत इंपॉर्टेंट एलिमेंट रहा
India's strategy.  Ok?
है भारत की स्ट्रेटजी को लेकर। ठीक है?
See, even now he gave us space.
देखिए अभी भी उन्होंने स्पेस हमको दिया।
Now whatever regime comes there, we have had
अब जो भी वहां पे रिजीम आए लेकिन हमारे
very good relations and we have been
बहुत अच्छे रिश्ते रहे हैं और हम तेल जो
buying oil from Iran.  There are cultural ties.
है ईरान से खरीदते आए हैं। कल्चरल टाइ रहे
And we have made investments and India has
हैं। और हमारा इन्वेस्टमेंट है और इंडिया
also told Israel
ने इजराइल से ये बोला भी है कि चाबारहार
not to attack Chabarhar Port.
पोर्ट पे आप हमला मत करिएगा। हमारा जो
After our IASTC, we had to make the IAC.
आईएएसटीसी है उसके बाद जो आईक हमको बनाना
Ok?  The Indian Middle East Economic
था। ठीक है? है इंडियन मिडिल ईस्ट इकोनमिक
Corridor was going to pass through Gwadar.  Well,
कॉरिडोर वो ग्वादर से जाने वाला था। खैर
that has been put on the back burner.  So
वो तो बैक बर्नर पे चला गया है। तो
Pakistan has reasons that at this time
पाकिस्तान के पास रीज़ंस हैं कि इस समय
we have a huge opportunity to
हमारे पास बहुत बड़ी अपॉर्चुनिटी है कि
separate Tehran from New Delhi.  But
तेहरान को न्यू दिल्ली से अलग करें। लेकिन
this is not happening because you are supporting and
ऐसा हो नहीं रही क्योंकि आप सपोर्ट तो कर
just showing it but you know, well
रहे हैं खाली दिखा रहे हैं बट यू नो अच्छा
New Delhi can catch this very well.
न्यू दिल्ली इसको बहुत अच्छे से जो है ना
India can say what it is
वो पकड़ सकता है। भारत जो है ये कह सकता
and can tell this to Iran.  See
है और ये ईरान को बता सकता है। देखिए आपका
who is your real friend?  Your real brother
असली दोस्त कौन है? आपका असली तो भाई
China, at least, is coming forward in Iran and saying
चाइना कम से कम ईरान के उसमें आ तो रहा है
yes, we are with you.  So
एकदम कि हां चलो हम तुम्हारे साथ हैं। तो
this India can definitely do leverage
यह भारत जो है वो लेवरेज बिल्कुल कर सकता
and after that preemptive strikes have
है और उसके बाद जो प्रिएटिव स्ट्राइक्स
happened.  Pakistan says that the Israeli
हुई है। पाकिस्तान कहता है कि जो इजराइली
actions are very wrong and
एक्शंस है वो बहुत ही गलत है और ऐसा होना
should not happen. And if we talk about Pakistan, then the
नहीं चाहिए और पाकिस्तान की अगर बात करें
actions are in
तो जो एक्शंस हैं
a way a protocol so that
वो एक तरीके से एक एक प्रोटोकॉल है कि
India can also act in this manner in the future.
भारत भी इस तरीके से एक्ट कर सकता है आगे।
That is why Pakistan is condemning Israel.
पाकिस्तान इसलिए इजराइल को कंडेम कर रहा
Right?  Because brother, Pakistan was afraid
है। राइट? क्योंकि भाई पाकिस्तान को ये डर
that India might
था कि भारत कहीं पाकिस्तान की न्यूक्लियर
blow up its nuclear site and I think that maybe
साइड ना उड़ा दे और मुझे लगता है कि शायद
work might be going on in this too.  So this
इसमें भी काम हो ही रहा होगा। तो ये हिसाब
is the accounting.  If this is their balancing act then it is fine.
किताब है। इनका बैलेंसिंग एक्ट है तो ठीक
That let's do a balancing act.
है। कि चलो बैलेंसिंग एक्ट कर लेते हैं।
But this did not work.  And let me tell you another thing
बट ये काम किया नहीं। और बात तो मैं आपको
that Pakistan is very boastful that
बता दूं कि पाकिस्तान तो बहुत ही बड़बोला
we have got the nuclear bomb. Do you think
है कि न्यूक्लियर बम हमने क्या आपको लगता
their minister says that
है इनके मंत्री बोलते हैं कि हमने शाहीन
why have we kept Shaheen and these missiles?
और ये मिसाइल ये हमने किस लिए रखी है?
Shaheen Shah Faridi Missile I am joking.
शाहीन शाह फरीदी मिसाइल मजाक कर रहा हूं।
We have kept it for India but they are
हमने तो भारत के लिए रखी है लेकिन इनको
very afraid that any day India and Israel
बहुत डर है कि किसी भी दिन भारत और इजराइल
together may destroy our nuclear
मिलके हो सकता है हमारा न्यूक्लियर
program.
प्रोग्राम उड़ा दे।
So the conclusion is that Pakistan is in danger.
तो कंक्लूजन यही है कि पाकिस्तान खतरे में